我們繼續讀第一次聖誕節
我們看到這個教會是有很多問題的
又有世界性的智慧
他們說我不用這些智慧
我有自己的智慧
還有有些人就想跟阿波羅
有些人就想跟彼得
有些人就想跟保羅
所以他有不同的分別
這個教會有很多分別
好像有些人想跟卡文
有些人想跟Vincent
有些人想跟Winnie
他們沒有這個Sense of Unity
然後上個星期我們聽到什麼
Sam就跟我們說
這個教會有不同的Sexual Immorality
有一個人就Dating他的什麼
他的Father's Wife
他Dating his Father's Wife
That's kind of weird, right?
是不是很奇怪?
It's a bit weird
Even in today's society, it's a bit weird
有沒有人想參加這個教會?
這個教會好像很精彩
很多戲劇
每個星期都有不同的戲劇出現
今天我們會看保羅
繼續提醒這個教會不同的東西
首先我們考考你
看看你怎麼會處理不同的問題
如果你回到你的小群組之後
之後你帶了一些Pokemon Card
有一個朋友就拿了你的Pokemon Card
你會怎樣?
你問他拿回,OK?
你問他拿回
還有呢?誰喜歡Pokemon Card?
Nixon,你會怎樣?
如果Daniel拿了你的Pokemon Card
他不告訴你,你不知道
你回到家才發現
噢!沒有了什麼卡?
什麼Pikachu?
你會怎樣?
如果Daniel拿了你的卡
你會打他?
嘩!真的打他?
不是假打?
OK,Let's go to the next scenario
你分房的時候帶了個足球
你的足球打爛了電視
嘩!你打爛了電視
你會怎樣處理這個問題?
如果你帶球打爛電視
你會怎樣處理?
你會賠償,你自己會賠償
OK,OK,Very good
我們問問Mentor
Mentor Maurice,你會怎樣?
你會馬上離開?
嘩!你馬上離開?
有閉路電視,你離開去哪裡?
是你一起踢的,所以你覺得要馬上離開
我們考考另一些
Nathan,你會怎樣?
如果你和Elias踢足球打爛電視
你會怎樣處理這個問題?
你會先問誰打爛電視?
如果是你打爛電視,你會怎樣?
你會承認的?
OK,如果是Elias呢?
找個Mentor去賠償,OK?
OK,Let's go to the next scenario
SCMP之前就有個Video footage
在學校打架
如果在小群組裡有人打架
Nixon打Daniel
嘩!你偷了我的東西,弄錯了
你會怎樣處理?
Lisa,你會怎樣處理?
如果你們女生的群組打架
你會怎樣處理?
女主不會打架,只是Gossip,對嗎?
I'm sorry, sorry
如果會打架,你會怎樣?
Lisa,如果真的打架,你會怎樣?
Forgive
如果有人打你,你會怎樣?
你打他,嘩!打他
女生會打架的
Faye,你會怎樣?
你會報警?
Eugene打你,你就會報警
有沒有人會報警?
有沒有人會打他,像Lisa那樣?
Vincent也會打他
Ok,Let's go next scenario
你的Mentor或Pastor
在小群組裡說的話是Heresy
It's not biblical
你會怎樣?
如果你分組了
你的Mentor或Pastor
Whoever is your leader
說的話不是正確的
Ok,Not biblical,你會怎樣?
先問問Hugo
Hugo和Martin好像很好聊
你會怎樣?
你會思考,Ok?
Ok,還有呢?
Next,Jose,你會怎樣?
你進了College A
然後有一個Mentor
說的話好像不是很Biblical
你會怎樣?
由得他?
Ok,誰會像Jose那樣?
先想想
誰會像Jose那樣?
就這樣理他?
Ok,還有沒有其他不同的方法?
是,真的不是Bible
耶穌可能不是死的
可能不是復活的
可能耶穌只是一個Alien
你會由得他?
Ok,Alright
今天我們看看哥倫哥的書
他們有什麼問題
Ok,Let's read together the next slide
We are going to read in English together
Ok,Ready? 1,2,3
If any of you have a dispute with another
Or do you not know that the Lord's people will judge the world
And if you are to judge the world
Are you not competent to judge trivial cases?
Do you not know that we will judge angels?
How much more the living life
Therefore if you have disputes about such matters
Do you ask for a ruling from those of the lay of life or scorn in this church?
I say this to shame you
Is it possible that there is nobody among you wise enough
To judge a dispute between believers?
Then instead one brother takes another to court
And this is in front of unbelievers
這個問題是什麼?
這個問題保羅描述
在教會有幾個人有一個dispute
有一個dispute,是不是?
可能有人拿了別人的Pokemon card
或者有人不小心打破了東西
是不是?
那他們的問題
保羅的問題是什麼?
保羅的問題是
為什麼你告這個人
是用外面的法律去告這個人的?
是不是?
那這個solution
保羅就是在問
你是應該在這個教會自己處理這個問題
還是去外面的法律去解決這個問題?
保羅正在描述這個情況
我們會討論一下
Let's go to the discussion questions
Number one
Was there a time you had a dispute with someone at church?
How did you solve, resolve it?
How did you resolve it?
Okay
And then question two
How do you think God wants us to resolve our issues at church?
好,兩個問題
Let's have four minutes to discuss
Okay, mentors, let's go to groups
Okay,有沒有人想分享有dispute at church?
Anybody have a good story?
Sam,你那裡有沒有東西要分享?
學校那些
Okay,分享學校那些
我summarize一下
我們有些取態就是
我不和別人接觸就沒有衝突
我們知道
就是免得不小心踩到別人的尾巴
我們就決定
不主動接觸就沒事
或者有些是什麼呢?
就是說
我都不夠他打
所以我不要亂得罪人
大概是這樣
How does God want us to resolve issues at church?
Okay,李帆涵
He probably wants us to talk it out
Can I just not argue and just talk?
Okay, communication is important
Okay, very good
還有沒有?
還有沒有有d...
Elias,你想講?
Oh, yeah
So,他說resolve our issues
我們可以問一下
Pastors可以有什麼解決方法
Cause sometimes pastors
他的intelligence會高過我們
Sometimes
Okay
我們pastors會用AI去
問問AI那些
是不是?
Okay
Let's go to the next slide
教會是有不同的問題的
是不是?
因為有人就會有什麼?
有問題
會有罪的
在教會
都會有不同的different issues
這個保羅
我們要describe what issues he's talking about
There's criminal cases
And there are civil cases
有沒有人understand what is the difference?
有幾個lawyer在這裡
Okay, what is the criminal case?
Okay, arguments
Okay, interesting
Interesting
Uncle Vincent
You wanna describe what civil and criminal cases are?
Criminal cases are based on
Penal law or criminal law of that jurisdiction
And it can be different in all jurisdictions
Civil cases are cases of dispute
That's quite correct
On those areas
But the disputes are actually based on
Years and years of case law
Okay
好
那保羅呢?
What do you think Paul is talking about here?
Do you think he's talking about
People in the church being criminals
And doing things against the Roman church?
Or do you think he's talking about
Within the church, there's a dispute
There's an argument
Or somebody
Stole somebody's 菠蘿包
Or蛋撻
Or 蛋撻太鹹
So there's a dispute
是不是?
不知道有鹹蛋撻的
Okay
So today we're gonna learn three things
Three things
第一是worldly judgment
Godly judgment
And the right judgment
三個judgment
Okay
我們說的就是worldly judgment
之前保羅就說
Why do you take your disputes
To people that are what?
Non-Christians
In front of non-believers
之前在Roman society
他們會在哪裏
有這個judgment court case
Okay
現在呢
現在如果我們有一個
Legal dispute
我們會去哪裏?
Court
Nearest court
High court
在哪裏?
在對面
走到對面就可以了
是不是?
之前呢
在這個Roman society
他們會有一個court
在market place那裏
即是city center那裏
Okay, city center
Like for example
你去那些European city
最漂亮的地方
平時是那些city center
如果有個court
在city center
那怎樣?
What is the result?
如果在city center
那會怎樣?
It is
每個人都會看到
Everybody will know
你有這個dispute
這個有這個dispute
每個人都會知道
他們之前呢
就是用這個
是a form of entertainment
嘩,好得意
他又罵這個
這個又不喜歡這個
這個又不開心
所以他覺得是一個entertainment
所以保羅呢
就不想他們有教會的dispute
就make it public
So everybody knows
每個人都覺得
嘩,這個教會怎樣?
每個人都和這個世界一樣
他們有dispute
我們世界都有dispute
The church is no different
和他們see it as entertainment
保羅的問題是
為什麼你教會裏面有dispute?
Why do you need worldly judgment?
Worldly judgment
因為worldly judgment
是用什麼value?
是用worldly values
Okay
And so Paul is wondering
Why not have godly values
to judge the things
that are having
the problems in the church
這個Corinthian church呢
我們look at next slide
他們好像我們
現在這個civil rights movement
是吧
It's about my body, my rights
所以他們Corinthian church裏面呢
都是這樣
This is my property
These are my things
你弄爛呢
你偷了呢
I have my rights
I deserve some sort of solution
Some sort of solution
所以保羅呢
就講next slide
Let's go next slide
Why do you have people outside judging
that are unbelievers
judging your case inside the church?
Or do you not know that wrongdoers
will not inherit the kingdom of god?
Do not be deceived
Neither sexual immoral
nor adulterers
or men who have sex with other men
nor thieves
nor the greedy
nor drunkards
nor slanders
nor swindlers
will inherit the kingdom of god
外面的人呢
是practice這些不同的東西
是吧
So why are we getting these people
to judge our church case?
這個是我們的ambassador team
這個ambassador team
如果我們的ambassador team
Sam呢
就和Hosea有些東西
Hosea呢
偷了Sam的豬扒包
是吧
跟著呢
Winnie呢
就覺得CY經常壓著她
是吧
不喜歡她的東西
跟著呢
Kaleb呢
就不喜歡他媽媽的東西
是吧
你煮的東西這麼難吃
For example
是吧
Carmen呢
就不喜歡Johnny的office space
她想Johnny的office space
為什麼她近這個窗
近這個門
如果我們的ambassador team
是有這些dispute呢
跟著去了high court
去了high court
你會怎樣
Cynthia你會覺得怎樣
如果那個
Court都不理你
這些case
是吧
又不喜歡豬扒包
又那個office
又喜歡她那個
又不喜歡那個
These are ridiculous
這個呢
就是保羅
和這個Corinthian church
這樣說
是吧
Why are you bringing your cases
to the unbeliever worldly court
第一呢
It is entertainment to them
第二呢
Everybody knows the business
within the church
第三呢
It is not a good witness
Ok let's look at the next slide
If you watched the dark night
The joker says
Let's not blow things out of proportion
這個就是保羅
和Corinthian church這樣說
When we bring our civil cases
outside the church
我們就會destroy
幾樣東西
第一呢
是我們的church unity
是吧
如果你blow up這個
你的office space
好過我的office space
跟著有個dispute呢
是吧
這個教會呢
will not be in unity
還有呢
如果Josea討厭Sam的豬扒包
跟著這個就
It's not a good witness
是吧
為什麼這個教會討厭豬扒包呢
這個好像
好像這個教會有點問題
是吧
跟著第三呢
It affects our Christ likeness
是吧
如果我們這些dispute
我們教會裏面
自己都不可以resolve到
Then we are not acting in Christ likeness
We are not forgiving one another
We are not loving our brother and sister
好
我們學了worldly judgment
第二呢
我們要學的是godly judgment
為什麼godly judgment是好的呢
第一是
There is protection
Within the church
如果我們在教會裏面
去resolve這些不同的civil cases
我們就有God's protection
God's protection
And it is within the church
教會裏面是有人的
有人就是有問題的
又有罪的
是吧
We are gonna have issues
But we need to learn to resolve our issues
Especially if it is civil cases
第二呢
為什麼godly judgment是好的呢
Elias
You learn to listen
During the sermon time
It is time to listen to God's word
Ok
第二呢
是godly judgment
It is from God's wisdom
神的wisdom呢
是高過人的wisdom的
Ok
God's wisdom is higher
God is all-knowing
All-powerful
You know
All-wise
The created
Uncreated
The creator
是吧
所以他的wisdom呢
是最好的
So why are we relying on outside wisdom
Worldly wisdom
When we have godly wisdom
第三個reason
保羅給他們的教會
是為什麼要有godly judgment
第三是
We are called to judge the world
It says before
Do you not know that the Lord's people will judge the world
Do you know that we will judge angels
他是說in the future
Right
In the future
When Jesus comes again
And he will judge the earth
We will be there with Jesus
As he judges the world
And so we should have godly judgment
Over worldly judgment
保羅呢
就是
He is placing this question
Let's look at the next slide
Before you sue your brother or sister in Christ
Ask yourself
Is my reputation
My comfort
Or my money
Worth more than the gospel's credibility
保羅是說什麼呢
保羅是說
The church is a witness
A witness for what god is doing
A witness for god's love
And the gospel
And so if our dispute
Is causing our witness
To be ruined
Then we need to do what Jesus does
And that is forgive others
To turn the other cheek at certain times
OK
So the last thing we're going to learn is
The right judgment
Right
Creates the right witness
OK
If our dispute
Is causing us to
Sorry
If our dispute is causing us
To have a witness that is not good
Then we need to consider
You know what we are doing
What we are doing
How is this
How is this dispute
Ruining the reputation of the church
Ruining how people come to know Jesus
Is it distancing people
From knowing the Lord
And so what we should do instead
Is we need to bear with one another
And we need to forgive one another
耶穌是這麼說的
是吧
祂說
By this we will know
That you are my disciples
That you love one another
What Paul is saying here
Is that no you should not
It doesn't mean oh
If somebody does wrong
You should just forget it
Right
Or let it go
No what he is saying is
That you should
Firstly
If we can
Take care of this problem
Within the church
Use godly wisdom
Right
The mentors
If there is a problem
The mentors should be able to help
And if not then the pastors
If not the youth pastors here
Then the board
Or the deacons
If there is a problem
Within the church
Then we should have the godly wisdom
To take care of it
Within the church
Not blow it up
Onto the SCMP
And be like oh
這個豬扒包不好
是吧
No
We should take care of it
Within the church
So that we protect the church
And the witness
Our witness is the most important thing
That we can bring people
To the Lord
If not
The people outside will say
Why do we have to go back to the church
This church has so many problems
They don't even have the wisdom
To solve problems
Right
That ruins the Christian witness
Let's invite Daniel to come up
Let's give him a hand
OK
So Daniel
How long have you been back to Explore?
Like 2 months
OK
Why are you back to Explore?
Nixon
OK
Nixon brought me here
Nixon brought you here
That's good
OK
What church did you go to before?
同福堂
OK
Very good
Welcome you to Explore
It's good to have you with us
Today we're talking about disputes
What is the dispute that you've had before?
You speak in Chinese
My biggest dispute is with my dad
It's not a big argument
But it has a big impact on me
I've loved music since I was a kid
I'm the principal horn of HKEPA
Two years ago I was talking to my parents
It's not an argument
But from what they said
They didn't support my development in music
They wanted me to follow their path in finance and business
It had a big impact on me
I thought my family would support me
But they didn't want to
I didn't talk to my family for a few days
I was very sad
My dad understood why I didn't talk to him
He didn't formally apologise
But he told me to do whatever I want
I've talked to him about his thoughts
It's not an argument
But it's clearly a dispute
I was very sad
I prayed every day
To help me find my path
There were many different voices
My conductor and professor
All wanted me to study music
But it turned out
The closest people to me didn't support me
I was very angry and upset
After talking to my family
They told me their thoughts on my career path
They also told me to do whatever I want
非常好
你祈禱吧
你求神幫助你們解決這個問題
非常好
我們給Daniel鼓掌
很快就要結束
下一頁
Paul結束這段話題
說你被洗了
你被祝福了
在耶穌基督的名義
和神的靈魂之下
Paul提醒了教會
他們被耶穌救了
因為這一點
神給了他們祝福
他們也應該給他們祝福
下一頁
神的祝福
我們被洗了
我們被洗乾淨
耶穌再次救了我們
被祝福
意味著我們像耶穌一樣
神給了我們聖靈
讓我們再次像耶穌一樣
我們被祝福了
這裡有張圖片
我翻了
我們被祝福了
We have been justified, we have been proclaimed to be righteous before the Lord.
And so here are the three keys, four keys for resolving conflict.
The first thing we need to know is we need to bring our issues to the Lord first.
好像Daniel這樣,他有這個issue和他爸爸,他就點了他的祈禱,
We need to bring our issues to the Lord.
Maybe you'll have issues with your fellow classmates or with your mentors.
What we need to do is we need to bring it to the Lord first.
第二句話,我們要明白,神給了我們祝福,
He's washed us, He's sanctified us, He's justified us.
God has given us grace, God first forgave us.
And so we need to forgive others.
第三句話,我們要給祂祝福,神給了我們祝福,我們也要給祂祝福。
我們是因為神的原諒,我們才能原諒別人。
最後句話,我們要放棄聖經,我們要放棄聖經。
Paul tells the Corinthian church, don't let your disputes destroy the credibility of the gospel or your witness for the gospel.
And in the same way, don't let our disputes, minor disputes affect others from coming to know Jesus.
Helping others to know Jesus and having them have the gospel is the most important thing.
So four things can get up, four things can get up.
Let's pray together as we end our session.
We don't have time for our response song.
Heavenly Father, we thank you for the passage from Paul today.
We know that in the church, we may have issues with one another.
But help us to not have worldly wisdom, but godly wisdom.
To rely on the Holy Spirit for wisdom, to help us solve the different issues that we have.
And most importantly, to know that you have given us grace.
And that we should also give grace to one another.
Give us the Holy Spirit to help us to love one another, to forgive one another, and to help one another in the midst of our different issues.
Lord, as we go into our small groups, may you bless us with the wisdom of the Holy Spirit.
As we discuss how to resolve different issues that we have.
Bless us, Lord, as we go. In Jesus' name we pray. Amen.